James Augustine Haran papers
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
James Augustine Haran papers
1890-1937
Ms Coll 59
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
1
The papers include degrees from Trinity College, Dublin; certificates of hospital training; Haran's appointment as Medical Officer in the East Africa Protectorate; various reports on the plague in Nairobi, Kisumu, Mombasa, and the Gold Coast; his work during the war as Deputy Principal Medical Officer of the East African Protectorate; and other reports and correspondence. Of note are a map of Kisumu showing plague areas, and a broadside on the plague in the Gold Coast. The collection also contains a manuscript on St. Patrick written in 1937.
Haran, James Augustine, 1869-1940
Biographical / Historical
James Augustine Haran was born December 16, 1869 in Limerick, Ireland. He received his bachelor's and master's degrees from Trinity College, Dublin in 1891, and his medical degree from Trinity College, Dublin, in 1895. In 1898 he was appointed by the British Foreign Office as a medical officer in the East Africa Protectorate. Administration of the Protectorate was transferred to the Colonial Office in 1902. In World War I, Haran was appointed a Major. Haran worked mostly in what is now Kenya where he handled several outbreaks of plague including in Kisumu, Nairobi, and Mombasa. He was also assigned to organize public health services against the plague in the Gold Coast. In 1913, he was appointed Deputy Principal Medical Officer of the East Africa Protectorate, and in 1914 he given the rank of Major in World War I. Little is readily available on his life after the War. He died in Bath, Somerset, England, in 1940.
Related Materials
James Augustine Haran, "Notes on some cases of plague which occurred in Nairobi [British East Africa] during the months of March & April 1902," 1902, Manuscript 20th cent+
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased 2017.
Scope and Contents
The papers include degrees from Trinity College, Dublin; certificates of hospital training; Haran's appointment as Medical Officer in the East Africa Protectorate; various reports on the plague in Nairobi, Kisumu, Mombasa, and the Gold Coast; his work during the war as Deputy Principal Medical Officer of the East African Protectorate; and other reports and correspondence. Of note are a map of Kisumu showing plague areas, and a broadside on the plague in the Gold Coast. The collection also contains a manuscript on St. Patrick written in 1937.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is available for research.
Africa, East -- Social conditions; Fumigation; Great Britain -- Colonies -- Africa, East -- Administration; Medical education -- Ireland -- Dublin; Medicine, Military; Tropical medicine; Mosquitoes -- Africa, East; Physical anthropology -- Africa, Southern; Plague -- Ghana; Plague -- Kenya -- Kisumu; Plague -- Kenya -- Mombasa; Plague -- Kenya -- Nairobi; Public health -- Ghana; Public health -- Kenya; Public health -- Somalia -- Kismayo; World War, 1914-1918 -- Africa; Broadsides; Correspondence; Diplomas; Maps; Reports; Physicians -- Africa, East; Patrick, Saint, 373?-463?; Simpson, W. J., Sir (William John), 1855-1931; Turner, George Albert, -1917; Trinity College (Dublin, Ireland)
- Medical education, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The papers include degrees from Trinity College, Dublin; certificates of hospital training; his appointment as Medical Officer in the East Africa Protectorate; various reports on the plague in Nairobi, Kisumu, Mombasa, and the Gold Coast; his work during the war as Deputy Principal Medical Officer of the East African Protectorate; and other reports and correspondence. Of note are a map of Kisumu showing plague areas, and a broadside on the plague in Gold Coast.
  - Certificates of clinical training, 1890-1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    The two large certificates state that James Augustine Haran "attended the practice" and the clinical lectures in three hospitals, the Hardwicke Fever Hospital, the Richmond Surgical Hospital, and the Whitworth Medical Hospital. All three hospitals are illustrated on the certificates.
  - Clinical training and training in vaccination certificates, 1891-1892 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Certificate from the Richmond, Whitworth & Hardwicke Hospitals signed in April 1892. Certificate for training in giving vaccinations signed in March 1891. The vaccination certificate, a small page, was found folded in with the hospital certificate.
  - Degrees, Trinity College, Dublin, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Three parchment degrees with attached insignias from Trinity College, Dublin, for Haran's baccalaureate degree in arts, master's in arts, and a preliminary degree in medicine.
  - Letters of recommendation from medical mentors, 1893 September (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Six numbered handwritten letters from former teachers and hospital preceptors, formerly attached by a pin.
  - Medical degree, Trinity College, Dublin, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Degree, Trinity College, Dublin, 1913 October (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Degree for passing an examination. This may be for the Doctor of public health (D.P.H.) that Haran later appends to his name.
- Career as a British medical officer in colonial Africa, Series II
  - Appointment as a medical officer, East Africa Protectorate, 1898 January 13 and February 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Appointment is from the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. At the time, Haran was associated with Barrington Hospital, Limerick, Ireland.
  - Report on Kismayu (copy), 1901 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Kismayo or Kismayu is on the east African coast, now part of Somalia. Haran's draft report, typewritten with changes in ink, notes that he first arrived in Kismayu in August 1900. The report concerns mosquitos in Kismayu and public health work to reduce their numbers. Haran also discusses the care needed for health officers who become ill. He says he will be doing a report on the town of Yonte. With the report are contemporary copies of two letters to the Principal Medical Officer, East Africa Protectorate dated, 1901 November 3 and 11.
  - "Some remarks on the recent outbreak of plague at Nairobi, March-May 1902", 1902 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Draft of a "confidential" report in ink, written in Nairobi (now the capital of Kenya), to be sent to the Secretary for Foreign Affairs and others
  - Letter from the Principal Medical Officer, East Africa Protectorate, congratulating the medical officers in Nairobi, 1902 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Handwritten letter to the Medical Officers in Nairobi during the plague, Dr. J. A. Haran and Dr. William Radford, conveying congratulations from the Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs "on the successful manner in which you combated the outbreak."
  - Map of the Kisumu Plague, by F. C. Kyle, 1905 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Kisumu (now Kisumu Town) is an inland port city on Lake Victoria, now part of Kenya. The 34x32 cm. map shows houses that were burnt and houses where the plague occurred.
  - Letter from Commissioner's Office, Nairobi, to J. A. Haran, Nairobi, 1905 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Typed letter conveys the satisfaction of His Majesty's Secretary of State for the Colonies for the work that Haran had done in combating the recent outbreak of plague.
  - "Tick Fever," typed manuscript, ca. 1905 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Carbon copy of a typed article intended for publication. Corrections in ink. 1905 is the latest date of the references.
  - "Narrative Account of the Outbreak of Plague at Kisumu", 1908 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Typed report by J. A. Haran.
  - "Public Notice" broadside on the plague in the Gold Coast, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Large broadside explaining what the plague is and the precautions to take. Printed by the Government Printer, Accra, Gold Coast Colony, West Africa. The Gold Coast was a British colony on the Gulf of Guinea in West Africa. It is now Ghana.
  - Official correspondence on Haran's service for the Gold Coast, West Africa, 1908 May 4-July 6 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Typed copies of three letters. The first is from Professor W. J. Simpson, Accra, Gold Coast Colony, attesting that he and Haran had arrived in February, and stating his appreciation of the work done by Haran in combatting the plague at Accra. The second letter is from John Rodger, Governor, of the Gold Coast Colony, to the Earl of Crewe, transmitting Simpson's recommendation of Haran. The third letter, from the Principal Medical Officer's Office in Nairobi, notes Haran's application to become a medical officer for Mombasa.
  - "Memorandum on the reforms necessary in the sanitary administration of Mombasa", 1912 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Carbon of a typescript emended in ink. Also a handwritten letter on the stationary of the East Africa Protectorate on the politics of management of Mombasa and mosquitoes. The writer is unidentified and appears to have written the typed manuscript. Both items were sent in an envelope (present in the folder) to Haran in Mombasa.
  - J. A. Haran, Mombasa, to the Principal Medical Officer, Nairobi, 1912 September 23 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    On what should be done "in view of the unwelcome appearance of Plague in Mombasa." Mombasa is on the coast of Kenya.
  - Letter of J. A. Haran to "the Hon. C. S." on fumigation of goods for export, 1913 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Typescript emended in ink on "fumigation of goods desired to be exported from infected areas." He discusses Clayton gas and cyanide fumigation.
  - "Summary of Action taken by, or under the instructions of the Deputy P.M.O. in connection with the present War from the outbreak of hostilities to the return of the Principal Medical Officer from tour, 1914 August 5-13 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Haran was appointed Deputy Principal Medical Officer for the East Africa Protectorate in 1913. Dr. A. D. Milne, the Principal Medical Officer, returned on August 13.
  - Appointment to the rank of Major in the Land Forces of the United Kingdom, 1915 August 18 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Certificate with seal from His Majesty's Command.
  - Professor W. J. Simpson, M.D., Report on Sanitary Matters in the East Africa Protectorate, Uganda, and Zanzibar, 1914 August (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Printed report (80 pages) "for the use of the Colonial Office." Has references to J. A. Haran. There are two inserts, one a typed letter from J. A. Haran, Mombasa, to the Principal Medical Officer, Nairobi, 1912 September 23. This has been given its own folder, Folder 18. The other is a draft list in ink of ships of the Admiralty and Germany, which has been retained in this folder.
  - "Annexure to Command Order No. 48" - Military officers in East Africa Command, 1914 December 18 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    This document lists the British military command in Africva beginning with Commander-in-Chief, Sir H. Conway Belfield, Governor of East Africa. Lt.-Col. A. D. Milne is listed as Principal Medical Officer, but J.A. Haran is not listed.
  - List of Medical Officers in the Service of the East African Protectorates, January, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Printed by Waterlow & Sons Limited, London Wall, London. Under the East Africa Protectorate, J. A. Haran is listed as Deputy Principal Medical Officer under Principal Medical Officer, A.D. Milne.
  - Reprint of George Albert Turner, "Some of the tribal marks of the South African native races", 1911 February (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Published in Transvaal Medical Journal. G. A. Turner, M.D., D.P.H., was the medical officer of Witwatersland Native Labour Association, Johannesburg.
  - Norman Roberts, U.S. Public Health Service, "Cyanide Fumigation of Ships", 1914 December 11 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Reprint from Public Health Reports published by the Government Printing office, 1914.
  - G. A. Turner, "Some Anthropological Notes on the South African Coloured Mine Labourers", ca. 1915 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Mimeograph manuscript, 89 pages. Detailed physical anthropology. Another copy with photographs exists at the Royal Anthropological Institute of Great Britain and Ireland. The manuscript was probably not published. Turner died in 1917
- Other materials, Series III
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1903, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    The 1903 partially-printed letter informed Haran that he was elected a foreign member of the Royal Societies Club, London. A letter from James Nash & Son, Estate Offices, Limerick, to Haran, Bath, 1926 March 30, involved legal matters. Haran's draft reply is on the back. The third item is from Debrett's Office, London, regarding Haran's entry for one of Debrett's directories. Two drafts of letters by Haran are on the back. There is also an advertisement from Debrett for bookplates.
  - "Regarding Saint Patrick", 1937 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Two copies, typed and mimeographed, each 5 pages. Unsigned manuscript endeavors "to identify the place names mentioned in the earlier part of St. Patrick's life."